Guide to the Oral Histories Documenting Yale University Women
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Farley, Margaret, 2009 February 10; Accession 2012-A-040
  Margaret Farley talks about her family background and upbringing, and the role of education in family life. She reflects on her own career expectations and the assumptions she made about her adult life, especially in light of her mother's experiences. After talking briefly about her own undergraduate experiences and becoming engaged to be married in her senior year, Farley then explains how she began to reassess what she wanted to do with her life, and how this culminated in discovering a religious vocation. She recalls the challenge of finding the order of nuns which suited her best, and why she took her final vows with the Sisters of Mercy. A lengthy account is given of her work with this order in Detroit during the Civil Rights era, and she pays tribute to the role models of female leadership she found amongst the Sisters.
  Farley goes on to explain why she applied to Yale for graduate work, and recalls in detail what it was like to be a female graduate student at Yale in the late 1960s and how this contributed to her growing awareness of gender issues. She also discusses how being an older, professional woman and a nun affected her life as a graduate student. The circumstances in which she was hired by Yale Divinity School to teach Christian Ethics are then described, along with the culture of the school during the 1970s. Much of the rest of her interview deals with the specific gender issues she encountered during her tenure at Yale, particularly the challenge of introducing feminist theology into the curriculum, implementing inclusive language, the debate surrounding the question of women's ordination, and the foundation of the Women's Center and the role it played in supporting and mentoring women at the Divinity School. An outline is provided of the ways in which the Women's Center and the Women Faculty and Administrators Caucus became a forum where women – faculty, administrators and students - learned together to strategize and organize on gender issues and to identify and implement women friendly policies at the School. Farley addresses the pressures she experienced when she was, for a considerable time, the only woman on the faculty, and the struggle to get tenure for her colleague, Letty R. Russell. She also touches on Yale's response to affirmative action in the early 1970s, and how she challenged salary inequity. More generally she recalls the battle to save the Divinity School from closure and her involvement in teaching in other parts of the Yale campus, notably the Medical and Law Schools. Finally, she speaks about the value and rewards of teaching, and the position of women in contemporary academic life, and how feminism and women continue to change and shape higher education.
  - Audiorecording, 2; ; 2 hours
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Forsberg, Joan Bates, 2009 June 9; Accession 2012-A-041
  Joan Bates Forsberg was born on the January 15, 1928, in Chatham, New Jersey., where her father was superintendent of schools. Her mother trained as a teacher; following her marriage she became a homemaker, though remained very active in church and community. Forsberg went to Endicott College, MA, with the intention of pursuing a radio broadcasting career, but transferred to Drew University when she received the call to ordination. She graduated in 1950. She was admitted to Yale Divinity School which, at that time, capped the numbers of women students to ten per year. She received her Master's in Divinity in 1953, by which time she had married a fellow divinity student, Robert Forsberg. She was ordained as a Congregationalist minister in 1954.
  For nearly twenty years Forsberg's primary role was as wife and mother, raising a family in New Haven's inner city housing projects, where her husband was part of a group ministry. During this time she was a social activist, involved with Connecticut Planned Parenthood and its campaign to legalize contraception in the state, which culminated in her involvement in Griswold v. State of Connecticut (1965). In 1968 Forsberg took up the challenge of procuring legal and safe abortions through her involvement with the Clergy Counseling Service for Problem Pregnancies. This period saw the development of her feminist consciousness, which ultimately led her to end her marriage.
  After working briefly at the Yale Divinity School's Continuing Education Center, in 1971 Dean Colin Williamson asked her to become the Divinity School's first Advocate for Women. Initially the position was combined with that of Registrar because of funding issues. In addition to carrying out the registrar's administrative duties, she was responsible for counseling women students, directing programs for women, teaching a course on Women and Ministry, and participating in the school's liturgical life. Almost immediately the Divinity School's Women's Center was established under Forsberg's leadership, the first of its kind at Yale University. In 1977 she was promoted to Assistant Dean and then Associate Dean for Student Affairs and Director of Admissions, positions she held till her retirement in 1993. She was appointed Lecturer in Practical Theology in 1974 and received a Doctor of Divinity from Berkeley Divinity School in 1978.
  Yale Divinity School established the Joan Bates Forsberg Scholarship in 1993 in honor of her distinguished career in social and pastoral ministry.
  Forsberg begins her interview by recalling her early life in suburban New Jersey, and the expectations placed upon young women of her class and generation. She speaks at length about her mother's life and her importance as a role model, and then recalls the childhood experience which first made her aware of gender discrimination. Her call to Christian ministry and ordination is discussed, and the changing role and empowerment of women within the church is a recurring theme in the interview. Forsberg returns a number of times to the difficulties of balancing marriage with ministry, since she experienced them in her own life as well as observing the struggles of her peers and, later, of her students. She reflects on how prevailing theological positions, specifically those of neo-orthodoxy, helped shape her identity as a woman. An account is given of her reasons for applying to Yale Divinity School, her experience as a student there, the prevailing social and political culture (particularly in respect of the attitudes to women amongst the faculty and her male peers), and the challenge of being a member of a tiny minority within the student body. The liminal status of women at the school is explored in her account of the history of women's accommodation on the campus. The 1953 Batchelder study on women at the Divinity School, and the ways that its findings related to her own experience, are addressed. Then she describes the sex discrimination which she herself suffered, especially when she married in her third year.
  Forsberg describes her life as the wife of a committed, radical minister and the challenge of raising a family in some of New Haven's poorest neighborhoods. A detailed explanation is offered of her role in Griswold v. Connecticut (1965), why she became involved, and how this helped shape her growing awareness of feminist issues in the late 1960s. She then explores the relationship between second wave feminism and the development of feminist theology.
  The major portion of the interview is devoted to Forsberg's twenty years as Advocate for Women and the work of the Yale Divinity School's Women's Center. She explains how the position came about and its evolution in the early 1970s, as the numbers of women students began to rise once the numbers cap on women was eliminated. Many of the pressing gender issues of the day are recalled: the campaign to appoint women on the faculty, the barriers to women's ordination, sex discrimination within the churches, consciousness-raising, the reworking of the curriculum to teach and then mainstream feminist theology, and the challenge of introducing inclusive language into the Divinity School's sacramental and liturgical life. Forsberg recalls her relationship with Dean Colin Williamson during the early years of the Women's Center, and the significance of Margaret Farley's appointment as the first woman on the faculty. The issues surrounding the appointment and tenuring of the feminist theologian Letty R. Russell are also covered. She pays tribute to the ways in which Russell brought together students, faculty and administrators to organize on gender-related issues. Forsberg recalls the responses of male students to feminist theology and activism at the School, and comments on the ways in which fissures created by race, class and sexual orientation complicated gender issues.
  - Audiorecording, 2; ; 4 hours
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Gersick, Connie Goldman, 2009 June 5; Accession 2012-A-042
  Connie Goldman Gersick was born in 1948 in Davenport, Iowa, and was raised in Rock Island, Illinois, where her father ran the family furniture store. She began her undergraduate education at the University of Michigan but transferred to Brandeis University at the end of her sophomore year to be closer to her boyfriend who was an undergraduate at Yale. They had grown up in the same small Jewish community and known each other since 6th grade. They married in June 1969 and Gersick dropped out of college to go live with her husband in New Haven. Whilst he completed his senior year at Yale, she got a job as secretary and assistant to Elga Wasserman, who had been hired by President Kingman Brewster to oversee the implementation of coeducation at Yale.
  Kelin Gersick graduated in 1970 and was admitted to Harvard graduate school; Connie Gersick returned to Brandeis, graduating magna cum laude in 1971. In her final year at Brandeis she was actively involved in the women's movement and, inspired by working for Elga Wasserman, chose a career in university administration, specializing in working with women. In 1972 she gained a M.Ed. in College and Adult Counseling at Boston University School of Education. From 1972-1975 she was Admissions Officer and Special Programs Officer at Radcliffe College, appointed by Matina Horner who had recently become the college president. During this time, Gersick had her first child, but continued in the post half-time.
  In 1975, Kelin Gersick finished his Ph.D. at Harvard and took a junior faculty position at Yale just as the Directorship of the Office on the Education of Women came vacant. At the age of 26, Connie Gersick was appointed its Director. She held the post for two years but then decided to return to graduate school as she believed a Ph.D. would enable her to progress more successfully in higher education administration. She gained a doctorate in Organizational Behavior from Yale in 1984, and during this time she had her second child. The family decided that the next move would be to further Connie Gersick's career, so they moved to California when she was appointed Assistant Professor of Management, and then Associate Professor of Human Resources and Organizational Behavior at the Anderson Graduate School of Management, UCLA, where she remained until 2001. Whilst at UCLA she spent a year as a visiting scholar at the Harvard Business School (1996-1997) and was Co-Area Chair, Human Resources and Organizational Behavior at the Anderson School (1997-1999). From 2001-2007 she was Associated Faculty at the Simmons School of Management. She was the founding director of the Women's Leadership Institute, an executive education workshop at UCLA. She is also a Research Associate at Lansberg, Gersick and Associates, and Visiting Scholar, Yale School of Management.
  Connie Gersick's work focuses on quantitative research in adult development; individual, group and organizational change and adaptation; and the effects of time and deadlines on work and learning. She is the author of many articles in this field and she has won a number of national awards for her research publications on group work and change processes. At time of writing she is researching a book called Journeys Into Womanhood: Life Lessons from a Pathbreaking Generation.
  After touching briefly on her background, Connie Gersick talks at length about the male undergraduate culture she encountered at Yale in the late 1960s and how many aspects of it prevailed even after coeducation began in 1969. In particular she describes what it was like to negotiate the social and sexual politics of the "mixer" culture. An account is given of how Sixties countercultural values began to infiltrate campus life when the admissions policy reforms begun in 1965 by the then Dean of Undergraduate Admissions, Insley "Inky" Clarke, opened up Yale to a broader spectrum of undergraduates. Her decision to drop out of college to get married is discussed, along with her first encounter with second wave feminism. She recalls the moment when she discovered Betty Friedan's Feminine Mystique and how it impacted on her recent marriage.
  Gersick discusses the work of the Yale for the Coeducation of Women and the issues surrounding coeducation, especially the pressures on the first cohort of women undergraduates. She recalls her return to Brandeis, her growing involvement in women's issues, and her first encounter with some of the major figures in second wave feminism, especially Alice Walker.
  Her work as Admissions Officer and Special Programs Officer at Radcliffe College is briefly described. Then Gersick talks at length about the political and personal challenges of the job as Director of the Yale Office on the Education of Women, in particular her interactions with feminist groups on campus and the Provost's Office. She pays tribute to a number of women in the Yale administration like Etta Onat, Betty Trachtenberg and Judy Hackman.
  Lastly Gersick talks about the experience of bringing up two children and the egalitarianism which she considers a hallmark of her marriage in the context of women's careers, and how these personal experiences have inspired her academic research into the culture of organizations and the challenge of changing institutional culture to enable women to flourish in the workplace.
  - Audiorecording, 1; ; 2 hours and 7 minutes
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Haseltine, Florence, 2008 March 3; Accession 2012-A-043
  Born August 17, 1942, Florence Pat Haseltine grew up, the eldest of four children, on the China Lake Naval Base in the Mojave Desert in California, where her father was a physicist. In 1960 she entered the University of California at Berkeley, where she majored in biophysics. She married a fellow biophysicist in their senior year and together they entered Massachusetts Institute of Technology graduate school. She earned her Ph.D. in biophysics in 1969. The marriage failed and immediately Haseltine applied to medical school. She entered Albert Einstein School of Medicine in 1969, where she began her involvement in the women's movement. She completed her medical studies in 1972. Her final year was spent at the University of Pennsylvania when her second husband, Alan Chodos, a physicist whom she had married in 1970, found employment in Philadelphia. She interned at the University of Pennsylvania, where her experiences formed the basis of her 1976 novel, Woman Doctor. When her husband's work took them back to Boston, she undertook her Obstetrics and Gynecology residency at the Boston Hospital for Women, where she began her lifelong commitment to women's health by setting up a feminist health center.
  In 1976 Haseltine was hired as an Assistant Professor in Obstetrics and Gynecology, and later in 1982 as an Associate Professor, Obstetrics and Gynecology and Pediatrics at the Yale School of Medicine, where she pursued clinical research on in vitro fertilization. While at Yale, she undertook a year of training at the Yale School of Organization and Management. Having failed to be awarded tenure at Yale, she became director of the Center for Population Research at the National Institutes of Child Health and Human Development at the National Institutes of Health. She commuted for many years between Washington, D.C. and New Haven, CT, where her husband, who was teaching in the Yale Physics Department, and their two daughters lived.
  In 1990 she was a founding member of the Society for the Advancement of Women's Health Research, which brought the issue of women's health to the national research agenda, successfully advocating for the inclusion of women in critical clinical trials. She has been the editor-in-chief of the Journal of Women's Health since 1992, and she edited a comprehensive report, Women's Health Research: a Medical and Policy Primer (Society for the Advancement of Women's Health Research, 1997). She has edited and authored many books and articles on reproductive medicine and women's health. In recent years she has extended her interest to include the health of women with disabilities. This resulted in Welner's Guide to the Care of Women with Disabilities, edited by Sandra L. Welner and Florence Haseltine (Lippincott, 2004). Dr. Haseltine founded Haseltine Systems Corporation in 1995, a company which designs products for people with disabilities. One of her designs is the Haseltine Flyer, a portable protective container for wheelchairs to allow wheelchair users to travel more easily. Together with Stephanie Pincus, Florence Haseltine established the RAISE Project, a national awards clearinghouse dedicated to recognizing the achievements of women in science, medicine and engineering. Florence Haseltine's work on behalf of women's health research earned her a Kilby Laureate Award in 1998 and many other accolades including election to the Institute of Medicine. She was named as a Weizman Honored Scientist and a Kass Lecturer, and honored by the American Health for Women Magazine, Prevention Magazine and the Ladies Home Journal.
  Florence Haseltine discusses her reasons for accepting a position at Yale, and the extent to which gender was an issue in hiring and retention of women at the Yale School of Medicine in the 1970s, a theme to which she regularly returns throughout her interview. She discusses at length the challenges, including salary discrepancies and other forms of discrimination, and the rewards of being a woman in an almost exclusively male environment, whether in the laboratory or at Yale-New Haven Hospital. In particular she reviews how the experience of pregnancy and motherhood impinged on her personal and professional life, and how it inspired her to lobby for daycare facilities at the medical school. She recalls how she taught the first college seminar at Branford College on women in medicine, and pays tribute to the women scientists she encountered at Yale, speculating about what price they may have paid for their professional success. She talks extensively about mentoring and what role gender plays in how mentoring is conducted, recollecting her own experience of "mentors and tormentors," as she describes them. Dr Haseltine discusses gender as an issue in the 1979 Felig plagiarism case. She talks about workplace politics in medicine and science at Yale and beyond, and the ways in which women can be excluded from executive roles, one of the reasons she took a year out to study at the Yale School of Management. She recalls her failure to secure tenure at Yale, and her reasons for accepting a position at the National Institutes of Health (NIH) rather than seeking a tenured position at another university. She talks extensively about her work at the NIH, especially proposals and initiatives she undertook that specifically benefited women in the sciences. She concludes her interview by discussing the growing role of women in science and medicine, and by outlining what she believes are the institutional changes that must be made in order to achieve gender parity.
  Note: Florence Haseltine was also interviewed in 1977 for the Oral History Project on Women in Medicine at the Medical College of Pennsylvania, now Drexel University College of Medicine (http://archives.drexelmed.edu/womanmd). The interview focuses on her life up to the time she was appointed at Yale.
  - Audiorecording, 2; ; 3 hours
    - Use copy, 1
  - Edited transcript, 1
    - Use copy (Box 1)
- Kirk, Elizabeth, 2007 November 1; Accession 2012-A-045
  Elizabeth Doan Kirk was born September 5, 1937, in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Her family had strong Quaker roots and both her parents were college professors. Her mother, Helen Bell Hole, taught English at Earlham College (1948-1970), where she was also Provost (1971-1972). Elizabeth Kirk attended The Westtown School, and then received her B.A. from Earlham in 1959; both are Quaker foundations. She then entered Yale as one of the members of the first wave of women graduate students in English admitted by the then Director of Graduate Studies, the medievalist, E. Talbot Donaldson, who became her doctoral supervisor. After completing her Ph.D. in 1964, she was an Instructor in English at Yale from 1964 to 1967. In 1967 she moved to a tenure-track position at Brown University, Providence, RI, when her husband was appointed Director of Rhode Island Historical Society, and spent the rest of her career there, becoming a full professor in 1980.
  Kirk held two distinguished professorships at Brown, first the Nicholas Brown Professorship of Oratory and Belles Lettres from 1989 to 1995, and then the Israel J. Kapstein Professorship in English, from 1995 until she took early retirement in 1998. She held many administrative appointments while at Brown. Most notably she participated in the historic settlement of Louise Lamphere vs. Brown University (1977)*, one of the most famous affirmative action cases brought against an institution of higher education in the United States. For many years she served as the English undergraduate honors advisor, and was instrumental in designing and implementing Brown's radical "New Curriculum." She served as Director of Graduate Studies in English, during which time she designed a graduate handbook which became a model of its kind. She was also the first woman chair of Brown University's English Department.
  Elizabeth Kirk's publications include Dream Thought of Piers Plowman (Yale University Press 1972) and Will's Vision of Piers Plowman (W.W. Norton, c.1990). She edited (with Mary J. Carruthers) Acts of Interpretation: the Text in its Context, 700-1600 (Pilgrim Books, 1982), essays in honor of her Yale supervisor and mentor, Talbot Donaldson. Kirk was honored with a festscrift in 2006, with the publication of Mindful Spirit in Late Medieval Literature: Essays in Honor of Elizabeth D. Kirk, edited by Bonnie Wheeler (Palgrave, 2006).
  Kirk received the Harriet W. Sheridan Award for Distinguished Contribution to Teaching and Learning at Brown University in 1997.
  *Louise Lamphere, an assistant professor of Anthropology at Brown University, filed a class action suit alleging sex discrimination under Title VII of the Civil Rights Act after she was denied tenure. In the subsequent out-of-court settlement in September 1977, Lamphere and three of her colleagues received tenure or damages, and the settlement mandated a procedure at Brown for women alleging discrimination, establishing a claims fund and an affirmative action monitoring process. Lamphere returned to Brown in 1979.